so very very basic question is
so
what people might ask and people do ask
um
you know what the buddhist teaching can
offer more than other legions and other
more than other legions and other
philosophies so what is different you
know because they all teach
some kind of
release from suffering and
happy life a meaningful life so what is
there the what is good what is there a
good reason to follow buddhist teaching
instead of others
well do other religions teach freedom from
do other religions teach freedom from
suffering
uh they would say yes like
happiness in the heavens
right okay so
so i think that's the difference the the
buddhist teaching offers you freedom
from suffering here and now without
having to wait for the heavens
um
and as the buddha himself said it's
directly verifiable
verifiable
by those who make the effort so that's
kind of the difference and actually yeah
you could probably sum up like that
that's also why for me as well i mean i
was in the beginning reading every
religion when i was interested because
i was trying to learn but that was
something that i could not come to terms
with was the idea of
you reach a certain point where you're
just left with faith and you just have
to have faith now and things will work
out and that was not good enough for me so
and that was not good enough for me so
i wanted basically something that would
not require faith as an endgame and
something that you can verify and then
you don't have to do anything anymore
and the only religion religion that i
found that was the buddhist teaching
some religions like taoism or maybe in
christianity they also require some
developing wisdom so it's not just
faith related well it is all within faith and
related well it is all within faith and
faith based like you develop wisdom up
to the point of
belief in god but you do not question
that and on top of it
and on top of it
doesn't matter what practice you do even
the most austere christian monks
it's still that practice is secondary to
the will of god who will dent free you
from suffering
and if if anybody is sort of
if if anybody is sort of
self-transparent and authentic that's
not a good deal you don't want any other
being to have a say in your well-being
and that's what the buddha himself sort
of insisted on
he said the gods themselves are subject
to same things you're subjected to
and that's the main difference so you
make your you make the effort yourself
for freedom and there is no intermediary
or some medium in between
so is there
there's no faith in buddhism or is also
element of faith uh the element of faith
as i said many times before it's the
faith you will have in a doctor
so you know you're ill
you you're seeking for the medicine
so you have faith that this doctor might
help you or that doctor might help you
to the extent that on faith you take the
medicine but not for the sake of taking
the medicine or for the sake of faith
you take it for the sake of health so if
you're not
curing as a result of the medicine then you
as a result of the medicine then you
don't have to keep that faith
but one has to have faith in the
buddhist teaching
well one has to have one has to apply
the medicine
so one has to have faith that the
medicine might work because otherwise
why would you apply it in the first
place
so the purpose of faith then it's not
just don't question it it's more like
don't question it it's more like
uh
yeah this person or this teaching might
be able to help me or help my
existential situation so thus
i will do what
the medicine prescribes i will keep the
precepts i will be virtuous i will
reflect on my actions
develop transparency towards my
intentions and see if it works
so that's the that's the extent of faith
so since you don't have a god or
worshiping the god
in british teaching
what is in the good reason to practice
virtue because like all the religions
have some kind of commandments rules
emphasizing good behavior for the sake
of heaven then yeah
yeah well the reason is the most direct
reason which is basically taming of your
mind because if you start practicing
buddhism or even learning about it
you'll see that the suffering
possibility of suffering any misfortune
in the world that you might experience
does not come from the world
comes from your mind
and the reason why it comes from your
mind is because that mind is not trained
and you cannot train the mind unless you
train your body first and actions to
invert you as simple as that
and when you have developed virtue and
have trained the mind then you cannot
suffer amidst the suffering
you just can't
think as
they would say original scene is
something like that apply to buddhism
no
but there will be that the funds doesn't
have its own beginning yeah yeah
so
but there's also teaching about five and
then also eight presets that's something
that uh posicas are going to
uh posicas are going to
take
i would say
commitment to those rules
so
what's so that we don't present it is something
so that we don't present it is something
oh this is if you want to be buddhist
you have to have five or eight precepts
so why for example should be following
five presets and also eight
um
it just depends how far you want to go
in in practice so
i guess for somebody who hasn't followed
any precepts five priests is a good
place to start because that's how you
will learn
see where the sensory strain lies
and the point of it then if you want to
take it further
you increase the restraint in terms of
the eight presets
but it's all for the purpose of training
because yes you will often have people
take them on a religious level like i
keep the precepts therefore i'm buddhist
or i'm born buddhist therefore i keep
the precepts i mean it's good but it
will not result in wisdom could we
quickly go through what these precepts
are uh so the five precepts the first one is
uh so the five precepts the first one is
uh no killing
no stealing
no
misconduct in central pleasures we can
define that
no lying
and no taking of
intoxicants alcohol drugs anything they
would sort of
contribute towards likeness of the mind
misconduct in sexual and sexual and
central pleasures means basically all
the person is not celibate they are
restrained so they don't
overdo it they don't
they don't allow their life to revolve
around pleasures and gaining pleasures
in seeking but actually exercising some
sort of
moderation and sense restraint
so yeah even then in itself just five
precepts uh if they can rightly can result in
uh if they can rightly can result in
taming your mind to some degree because
that's that's where it starts really
the bodily actions and choices we make
on account of them
you're trying to train an animal
if there is no discipline saying no
patience waiting enduring just let it
eat whenever you want it's not going to
listen to you
same with the mind
if you act whenever there is a desire or
a thought towards it and no restraint
uh even fear of enduring that little
discomfort of saying no to yourself then
the mind will keep doing that and it
will be controlling you so
that's why that needs to be developed
it's not going to happen magically like
uh
miraculously it will just stop on its
own because that's not what it does
so these are the five and then you also
have yes so the eighth precept is the third
yes so the eighth precept is the third
precept the misconduct in centrality
becomes full celibacy
uh and then you add another precept like
you don't eat after the noon
so like
slightly increased moderation in eating
um
then don't uh
like sleeping on high and luxurious
places which is basically more like
again on a practical level than just
indulging sleep
you know have a slightly less
comfortable bed they will prevent you
from laying in it for 12 hours and stuff
like that
because that all just contributes
towards mental and physical sluggishness
and the beautification so
again being overly concerned about your
central appearance so
uh beauty uh perfumes uh another added
precept to the five is that
entertainment so which is
so which is
shows dances music stuff like that
10 precepts is uh
uh that's like when um when a person
kind of joins the order as a novice as a
beginner so then you give up money
gold silver
valuables like that you can trade with
money basically
you don't handle it so you're kind of um
not as
independent i suppose in that sense just
creates even a greater sense of urgency
yeah and what's the
that's the city that's it
too yeah everyone is broken
yeah to become
entertainment and
beautification separate role yeah
sometime yeah the one of the eight is separated
yeah the one of the eight is separated
into two so you get nine and then you
give up the money as ten
nine that doesn't exist yeah
so the main purpose behind these
precepts is basically to tame your mind
to
well yeah i suppose yeah yeah to see
things clearer like as i said even if
you don't necessarily
look hey
drama
even if you don't have some you know
lofty goals in terms of practice
just being able to say no to yourself
and endure your own state of mind
that's an accomplishment
the life will be much better
because yeah the mind doesn't listen to
you you know it's nice when it's in a
good mood but it's not nice when it's
not in a good mood but you're paid with
it you have to endure it
the most people's concerns revolve
around trying to uh change the mind or
control the mind and make it obey them
but that's not a problem the problem is
that's not a problem the problem is
simply that you want
mind to be certain way
and then you resist it when it's not
that way so it's on you if you stop
resisting it
if you learn how to be patient and
endure it nothing that the mind can
throw at you can bother you
so that's that's the whole idea of like
you know learning how to disown it
correctly because uh the idea of that uh ownership
because uh the idea of that uh ownership
that would often talk about it's the
idea of control
you want to control things that are not
in your control and do you don't want to
let go of the idea
that they are in your control so that
that's like you suffered twice as much
that doesn't mean now you just let go of
everything just surrender no don't let
go of the precepts
don't let go of of taming that mind
but don't confuse it as something that
belongs to you because it doesn't
and what you're talking about now is
non-self in it exactly
yeah that's
again even the not that's why we
wouldn't necessarily or quite often
would not even talk about
always ourselves in ourselves and
provide answers to that because it's not
the point of of answering an
intellectual query it's more like
if you train correctly
tame your mind practice sense restraint
your experience will start approximating
the experience of not-self and
eventually it will be the experience of
non-self the non-control not like
negation of everything nothing is my
problem or like no i'm not trying to
control things that i know are not in my
control nor do i suffer on account of
them when they change
because you suffer is when you still try
to control them
how do you know you're not you're in
non-self sorry how do you actually know
you're there
in a free world non-self
uh by i suppose yeah by fulfilling the
training and not being able to suffer on
account of your mind changing
so it doesn't matter how your mind
changes it doesn't take you uh with it
and then you know you're not affected
anymore and that's what not self is
when sensual desire doesn't move you
when disagreeable things don't overwhelm
you and cause your will
when nothing to do does not scare you bore
nothing to do does not scare you bore
you and fill you with anxiety
when you are at ease with your own mind
and whichever state it's in
um
correct me if i'm wrong i believe buddha
never talked or didn't
speak much of um happiness
rather he spoke um or freedom from suffering
he spoke um or freedom from suffering
this is what you're saying now isn't it
yeah basically
basically
happiness comes when you undo everything
that makes you suffer
but if you start talking about happiness
people that just want to go straight
into happiness without
undoing everything that makes them
suffer so that that's why you avoided it in
so that that's why you avoided it in
that way
it seems that buddhism also can happen
like two extremes you have the ones
who take the rules quite religiously
like five pieces and so on that's
especially in asian countries
and then you have a people who maybe in
the west who just think believes me just
about coming the mind and
meditating but they don't purify the
virtue yeah so the buddha didn't go to
these two extremes yeah that's that's
that's why like if you if you do it for
the reasons of practice and mind
development you will find the right
balance between the two um
yeah that's something you i mean you can
just teach people but it's up to every
individual to really clarify that and
and do it rightly
generous advice it seems that uh let
people in buddhist time they were
following five precepts
and uh uh
eight presets
so that's kind of it's interesting to
see this uh for the buddha was
emphasizing that one
um
at least once a week let's say and
that's one thing we try to emphasize in
the past like a group
um
when we couldn't say something more
about a presets why one
should take at least once a week eight
presets
well for the same reason why would one
would be keeping the five
in the first place so as i said it's
just a it's just an addition an increase
of restraint if person does keep the
five precepts and wants to practice then
yeah it's good to take on eight because
if you just immediately go into full
sensory strain you might not be able to
to do it so it's like just to train
yourself to gradually
uh increase
wholesome ways of saying no to your mind
and gratuitous pointless desires that
the mind uses to control you with
and also yeah to see are you scared of
doing it
are you are you scared of saying no to
like things that you know are not
necessary but you're kind of used to
certain habits
sleeping long eating whenever you
feel like it not necessarily when you're
hungry scratching the itch whenever it itches
scratching the itch whenever it itches
can you endure it for even you know a
day so if you can't then that's that's the
so if you can't then that's that's the
work outline for you that's exactly what
you need to train in where is the border
line between
being a good person and a bad person
okay making five precepts
you know there's never good in killing
and lying and so on
what about like let's say listen music
you know is this oh no that's not that's
not now on the level of being good or
bad that's more like on the level of
that's more like on the level of
uh training your mind now so there's
nothing wrong with music or
things that you know it precepts cover
but there is a lot wrong with it if you want
there is a lot wrong with it if you want
to tame your mind to go beyond desire
so
but that's what needs to be done
gradually
there's a lot of suffering in taming
your mind yeah
so you're actually suffering yeah in the
same sense like you know you go to a
doctor and he tells you the reason for
your illness is your bad diet
so first you need to start eating right
things and you know avoid lots of other
things they used to give you pleasure
stop drinking and going out you're going
to suffer a lot more but then you're
going to become
cured and then you won't suffer at all
so it's like getting worse before you
get better
taking a bit of medicine they will kill
you in the meantime it's going to make you
in the meantime it's going to make you
feel miserable there are people living
in buddhist time that they kind of had
the same questions and
it's not that everybody will suffer on
account of it or that everybody suffered
to the same extent
uh the amount of your suffering will be
determined by the amount of your
addiction towards sensuality
so
the the the weaker the addiction the
less the suffering will be the stronger
the addiction the stronger the suffering
will withdrawal it's exactly the same
same thing
if you're kind of you know
able to say no to yourself you're not
going to suffer a lot more when you
start increase that precept and sense
restraint but if you've been running
around wild and just acting whenever
there was an itch and whenever there was
an intentional pressure oh you'll suffer
a lot yeah
could that be directly connected to
karma the concept of karma
well no i mean the concept of karma has
kind of been taken quite quite a bit out
of the context it's connected to the
concept of the direct karma of your
choices so
so
you have not have become so addicted you
would not have become so addicted if you
haven't been perpetually choosing
things out of your addiction as simple
as that an addict is not born and added
he becomes so through on actions and
chasing pleasures in an unrestrained
manner so that's that's that the responsibility
so that's that's that the responsibility
so yeah it's very calm related but not
in that eventual retribution sense or
something like that or what you've done
life times ago or something how people
like to believe and sort of use it to
explain why things that happen no it's
just if you keep choosing things out of
if you keep choosing things out of
sensual desires central desire is
something that's controlling it if you
keep acting out of anger and ill will
and irritation means those states of
mind are controlling you you're not able
to to to withstand them without acting
out so there's a personal subjective
so there's a personal subjective
viewpoint or is a buddhist viewpoint
that's the uh let's say early suta's
point so the early buddhist teaching
point not necessarily if you google buddhism
not necessarily if you google buddhism
today there's gonna be a lot of stuff
that has nothing to do with what the
buddha was teaching so i don't know
where you're coming from with that
question that's why i'm specifying it
well it's kind of specific because who
he judged to find for the censor
sorry he judges and defines what he said
that's why he laid out a teaching
revolving around it that's why you do
need to take it on trust
see if this is the addiction an addict
will not necessarily see it but if eric
develops some self-awareness and starts
looking for help
and then here's the way of talking about
the addiction recognizes some parts of
it still not convinced but starts doing
it then he'll become free from it and
then he won't need buddha to tell him
any further because he verified it for
himself but yes that certain degree as i
said before you came of faith is
necessary not like oh believe the buddha
but more like believe that this doctor
has the right medicine but the only way
to find out is to start doing it
you cannot be sure that he's the right
doctor that will cure you until you
apply the medicine the way he says you
should apply it
so faith for somebody who has applied
correctly the buddhist teaching
disappears it becomes confirmed
knowledge that this works
in terms of taming your mind that's it
directly verifiable
so we stay uh nobody in those five
precepts uh kind of sounds quite clear when you
uh kind of sounds quite clear when you
become them one to three to five
or eight but in practice sometimes
something's a bit challenging
let's say the first one you have in
tunisia or assisted suicide
so how we then
i mean how often that happens to people
that's not really a thing you have to
worry about but again it's it's uh
no killing
so it's quite clear yeah you don't you
don't kill as simple as that it can
happen for example uh
uh maybe with animals that you know we
have aging again you don't kill you
don't yeah
so you can have it quite often
also i think the triple gem
is a very um
i don't know it's a very popular concept
isn't it everybody knows that buddhism
in the triple gem could you say a few
words about that
for three refugees yeah three refuges
yeah ah they're right but they are i
mean as right yeah
the uh well like the buddha the dhamma
and the sangha so the buddha the refuge
to the buddha is the doctor so you're
taking refuge in the buddha well yeah
again even that see
you know taking refuge back in the
sutures meant oh okay no i know that
this doctor is making sense i'm going to
do this let me remember remember me as a
follower of your teaching kind of i took
refuge in what you're teaching i'm going
to do it for the rest of my life because
i see benefit of it that's what it meant
but now it means basically the same as
you know declaring yourself a christian
or something else similar just oh i took
refuge and i'm a buddhist i was like
yeah but
and often people would be taking refuges
and not even keeping the precepts
they're just these empty declarations
the buddha is the doctor the dummies
he's teaching and the sangha is the
disciples that followed it and cured
themselves that's it
so it's like the sangha the refuge in
sangha means ah okay so there are there
are other people that uh that did it
successfully so i take refuge in the
idea of that so that i can do it
successfully because it's possible so
actually that completes full circle so
only then was probably established when
the anikundanya the first one
the first person could go the right view
after this new teaching then then really
they said that the
dhamma will start turning
so it's kind of really completed because
it doesn't
mean very much just to have buddha in
dhamma if there's not
somebody else will get awakened by those
teaching so it's a complete conventional support
so it's a complete conventional support
isn't it yeah
yeah yeah
yeah
yeah i mean yeah exactly if you have
access to those who have
follow follow the instruction of the
doctor and cure themselves then yes you
can learn from them extra
but it's it's not on the level of you
know devotion or something that just
people declare and uh feel saved on
account of it you still have to do the
work
in the fourth presets we have also
usually it's kind of loosely translated
no lying but we know it's more it's
actually says in pali wrong speech which
includes lying
includes yeah that's that's that that's
probably the the most practical one
that's why often even in the suttas it
would be expanded
that that particular one because that is
like in the society what people would be
struggling with so it's taken online but
yeah not not gossiping
pointless speech harsh speech
spreading rumors offensive so it's just
practice of sense restraint when it
comes to choosing things you're going to
say and why you're saying them
so that means again you're kind of
adding a layer of that restraint there
is you know like the physical aspect of
it you don't do things with your body
but now there is this verbal aspect
where you just have to endure wanting to
say something but you know it's rooted
in the wrong reasons so the mind is
pressuring you to do it
and you you feel and like even if nobody
blames you for doing it if everybody
expects you to do it you know that it's
rooted in the pressure of your mind
that's exhibiting and that's why you
don't do it
because no other way you'll be able to
learn it
but surely you can speak angrily to
someone and have a calm heart and do it
for their benefit to get through the
layers of ego
uh well again not according to to the
early suitors not according to the to
what was taught originally because it's
a kind of a contradiction in terms
you're either angry mind no you can't
mind no you you raise your voice to make
it to make the effect well raising the
voice does not necessarily equal anger
so what do you mean by raising the voice
well it depends to what degree but that
to some degree you can show anger by a
loud voice but be calm inside for the
benefit of another person right well no
i don't agree with that because i agree
with the part you can raise your voice
but i don't agree that you have to raise
your voice when you're angry or that
raising your voice means you're always
angry no it's just occasionally you you
have to
cater your intonation to the other person yes
your intonation to the other person yes
exactly and you can do that
without being angry exactly but that's
the point
well no but if you're angry you can be
perceived as angry oh yeah no that
doesn't matter that doesn't matter yeah
if you're truly not angry that that's
fine even if everybody thinks oh he's
harsh and angry
but what i'm trying to clarify is as
long as you know as i said there might
be a justification to raise your voice
to make a point
and externally everybody will see that
and maybe will not even be thinking
you're angry but you know you are angry
and that's why you shouldn't do it oh no
i agree equally if you're right exactly
you have people who are very angry but
speak in a very you know
psychotherapeutical soft trained manner
full of anger and ill will but never
express it
so it's like speech is the result of it
so yes there were cases even in the
around the buddhist time where some
monks were just harsh the way they were
speaking and saying things
and people thought
they were really upset
and the buddha said well no just certain
habits don't necessarily change and if
there is a purpose even the buddha
himself was often you know admonishing
monks quite fiercely
but that doesn't exactly that does not
equate that you're angry internally so
yeah and good uh standard is also it has
to be helpful to the listener
yeah that's the main requirement yeah so
yeah well you will know that if you're
truly not angry you will know where it's
rooted like if you're not angry
you will not have problem not saying it
if you know it's not going to be heard
or helpful or it's going to fall on
their fears
usually people can't see all of these
implications because they're already
angry so
so
yeah you must never act out of anger but
it doesn't mean you will always speak
softly or gently or agreeably for that
matter training dogs isn't it exactly
yeah children
it's it's the same i mean yeah
i think the most difficult and
problematic for most of people is
actually idle chatter sometimes it's
difficult to know what about separating
between two speeches or speak dharma or
being quiet yeah
or just what is different like either
speech you know where is the borderline
can we talk about
politics and football
or
well borderline is always where your
intentions are are you the one
initiating it why are you doing it
because you're bored or you can't bear
the awkward silence all these pressuring
things in your mind that you're giving
into if somebody else starts it and if you
if somebody else starts it and if you
don't reply you'll be considered really
rude then that's a different reason then
you would as would say you speak enough
to sort of please the other person but
not to add more to it
so it's it does come down to knowing
your intentions and why you're doing
what you're doing whenever you you're
choosing to do it white lie
white lie
it's a lie
yeah that doesn't mean now you're just
going sort of spouting truth in
everyone's face all the time
it's just like money is beneficial if
asked you say it if all of you don't
need to say it you don't need to stick
your nose in so good life sorry so are
there good lies
uh not if it's rooted in intention to
lie no but if it's rooted in in the
no but if it's rooted in in the
intention of saving the other person
pain if it's still a lie
if it's still a lie
so it's still against the precept it's
still against that that training precept
the training
you don't have to say it but you
certainly can't afford to not lie ever
we generally i don't know
um we generally try to find ways to make
ourselves better to make our uh
circumstances better to somehow improve
ourselves to
we're striving for perfection and uh
in this sense the buddha's teachers is
very teaching is very radical because um
there is no you know there's no goal
somewhere out there
yeah well it's very radical in in the
sense that life is very radical it's
just the people ignore those certain
aspects the three divine messengers you
know sickness aging and death you might
not live to be 50 60 70 80 and even if
you do even that will feel quickly when
it comes
you know people get sick
young people get sick and die so it's
like presumption
that we're going to live a long time
that you're going to have enough time
for everything
and even then you kind of implicitly
think you're never going to die in that
sense like because if people would start
like because if people would start
thinking about that
even on a daily level
they would be making very different
choices eventually they would not be
able to kind of live carelessly
and um
like disregarding things and so on and
or even selfishly in that sense yeah
so that's that's how the buddha himself
turned to the practice when he saw the
old person sick person um and dead
person basically
like the inevitable just you cannot
it's not something you can even conceive
how to avoid
source of buddhism offers quite strong
this kind of monastic movement so how
much choice essentially if you want to
become a monk or
one can actually practice analyze drive
you as a late person uh theoretically
the right view you can get is a lay
person and even you could free yourself
from central desires as a lay person
but that's again you know
that was hard thing to do
in the buddhist time as a lay person
without having
you know play life so busy and
overwhelmed as they are today
so it's gonna take effort and
determination one way or the other
usually i would say the monastic life is
maybe a short cut well supposed to be
shortcuts oh no no no no it's more like
a
an amplification it's not a shortcut to
anything it's just going to amplify
things sooner for you
so
in that sense yeah i suppose
it may be short in the time but uh not
necessarily um
um
but there's a monastic life
contradiction to
practice compassion in the outside world
well it depends on the definition of
compassion well charity
well charity
yeah that's good
yeah that's one definition of compassion
that's one definition of compassion
another definition that the buddha
himself had was the the problem in the
world is not
lack of charity and lack of compassion
the problem is desire and people acting
out of it and doing bad things to each
other out of desire now imagine there is
a group of individuals that free
themselves from desire on account of
teaching and teaching others how to free
which they could do bad things to others
that's the cleanest compassion you don't
need to do anything to others if you're
free from your yourself completely free
from desire taught others how to be free
from desire that's the greatest
contribution because that's directly
uprooting the actual problem of the
world which is human desire but isn't it
rather infilo
sorry i find it very interesting it's
all about me
well that's what yeah what you're
telling me it's all about me so i mean
yep where's the heart in this process well
where's the heart in this process well
that's that's the whole point kind of
whether you take it to be on the level
of the heart or helping others you do it
because you want to so it's still about
you being nothing having given you connected
being nothing having given you connected
and obviously
doing things for other people is for
yourself as well yeah so that's quite
clear but still it seems very insular is you
but still it seems very insular is you
know peace be within well
well peace is not just within it's also
without right right right
well that's the point it's outside
because it's not inside is the root of
the problem
it's like you have a polluted ocean
because the streams on the top of the
mountain are polluted not because
somebody's polluting the ocean
all of that eventually ends in the ocean
so the society is polluted but it all
comes from the individuals
so if all the individual streams would
learn how to purify themselves from
desire ocean cannot remain polluted
anymore so yeah it is very insulin
but even even like in the most uh
mundane terms that's putting the
sort of committed practice to the side
again even if the ocean would be told
how to keep the five precepts
if somebody is to be repeating it enough
and teaching the value to people the
world would be a better place if you
teach people how to behave slightly less
out of their desire slightly less out of
their ill will
careless speech intoxicants and
everything else generally the community
would be nicer if certain virtues
standards of virtue virtues are upheld
and the only way to do that is when
people learn the value of it
it's easy to practice virtue if you know
why doing the four
yeah not just because you might be
watched by someone on there yeah that
works only
occasionally for a small group of people
and not always yeah
the fear of authority and so on
also we can
hear very diversified uh teachings
within what's claimed so called buddhism
what's claimed so called buddhism
coming yeah today
and but now
what retro starts as a beginner what is
the source what interior one should
uh listen or read
where is the main source of the kitchen
yeah i mean like as
as i said you google buddhism today and
probably 95 of it
will be very removed from what the
buddha was actually teaching
and again what the buddha was actually
teaching is something that people at
least agree upon in a in a certain
sense that they know
certain sutas and scriptures they would
say were kind of the oldest the closest
to to to what he was saying
and uh no matter how different schools
have evolved they do recognize that that
did come the first
so in that sense that's the closest to
the buddhist instruction you can get
even then with you don't really
necessarily know that that's right but
you have to begin somewhere you have to
follow the doctor's prescription
somewhere and uh that's the that's that that's the
and uh that's the that's that that's the
sutures so students are such a it's a
huge collection this one has mine's just
kind of afraid intimidated by it and
yeah the style and yeah
uh do one has to be almost like academic
to his history with other suitors no no
it's it's depends on the person really
and the inclinations if that's what
keeps you engaged yes if not
there is again so much
suitors for beginners google it so many
websites so many translated books
uh you just have to actually start
reading it and making the work and
trying to understand it and then
rereading it and reading it but yes
ideally would be nice if you just have
somebody tell you what to do
or like direct answers to all of your
questions quickly that you have but one
way or the other you still have to do
the work so
so it's not something you can avoid
reading and studying them
for the sake of understanding
for the sake of that clarity mostly
having the buddha is the teacher
fundamentally uh but what about
uh but what about
is it good to have
another teacher like a living teacher
around well yeah but i mean
well yeah but i mean
you don't necessarily know whether what
he's saying is right or not
so even that's taken as i said
the um
as a possible contribution to the
whatever medicine they would have
prescribed so but you still have to do
it yourself so it's not about finding a
teacher they will sort of make your
practice easier or
lighter it's more like clarifying the
it's more like clarifying the
instruction if you're clear enough you
don't need a teacher if you're not clear
enough seek the clarity but you still
have to do it
so it has nothing to do with the person
telling you
it doesn't um i don't know i think
most teachings usually begin with the
four noble truths
would you
say that's
basically you understood the instruction
so it's not
it's not you start with them then you
move on to something else
if you understood four noble truths
basically you don't need anyone's help
anymore you know exactly what to do
you know exactly where the cause of
suffering is rooted
and you know the answer is craving of of
your own mind not the world but
until that's clear to you
you haven't seen the four noble truths
so could you when we first say well
right for the four noble truths the
suffering the origin of suffering the
cessation of suffering and the path that
would lead to that cessation
but it's really just
one truth of understanding where some
where suffering is
because most minds would think suffering
is in
things the world the world
others
this or that
but there is only one cause for
suffering so if the suffering is present
in your mind
it's because that cause is present in
your mind
and that causes craving
we can't suffering with healthy
sorry can't suffering be healthy if i'm
suffering i will strive to be a better
person would be a very simple announcement yeah
would be a very simple announcement yeah
yeah so as i said that would be the
suffering of taking the medicine that's
unpleasant no no no no
i'm suffering therefore i will go and do
something about the suffering not
necessarily cause it if i if i see
suffering in the world i will therefore
go and
do something about it instead of cease
that suffering within myself right no
but suffering in the world is not the
suffering in yourself that's not the
same thing
well inside you're going to be suffering
you can go and help the world and
diminish world suffering even if you
don't suffer internally it has nothing
to do with each other
the internal suffering is what we're
talking about but it's a motivating
factor well no the motivating factor is the
well no the motivating factor is the
desire and you want to definitely
turn it
going back to my analysis of good and
bad lives
it's also you've got good and bad
suffering again we're talking about two different
again we're talking about two different
levels of suffering the suffering the
four noble truth of suffering is the
internal suffering the internal um
dis-ease uneasiness of the mind it's not
the suffering of the world and that you
might perceive in others
so what i'm saying is the suffering you
refer to
is not much really to do with what we're
talking about in a sense of if you were
to approve to the suffering inside of
you remove the craving you can still help
remove the craving you can still help
the world as the buddha himself did
and diminish their suffering for example
i'm i'm suffering because i'm hungry
now i know buddha decided to starve
himself and then went into moderation
and then decided to
eat a lot
now oh have i got that wrong
oh have i got that wrong
sort of but it's it's but but okay but
because i'm hungry i'm not going to
therefore practice attachment
non-attachment i will go and do
something like go and get work so i can
feed myself right right so what again
that's two separate things uh
hunger is not the cause of suffering
and that's
if you think that is because you haven't
seen the four noble truths and that was
the the insight that the buddha saw that
nobody else did
discomfort in the world is not the cause
of suffering
hunger is not the cause of suffering
words of others misfortune being beat
and thrown it's not the cause of
suffering craving phenomenon of craving
being present in your mind means
presence or so i think i suffer a lot
looking at the world as it is it's
basically how you react to it yeah you
know suffering exists and it's you how
you react to it you know if you let it
affect you but i'm saying that you can
let it affect you and you can do
something positive yeah but you don't
need to suffer because of suffering of
others you know you can know it's bad
but you don't let it affect you to a
level where you would suffer on account
of others and you can still go and help
them it's not required
it's not required
if suffering is required to make you do
something about it
again means you haven't understood the
suffering
so hunger yeah you could go and work and
eat but you don't need to suffer on
account of it which means you won't
suffer on account of the pressure of
work and having to earn
because what if i don't get enough food
well hunger does not bother you in terms
of suffering death does not bother you
in terms of suffering
because even death in itself is not the
cause of suffering illness is not the
cause of suffering tanha means suffering
first noble truth that's why it's like
the universal truth that nobody else
could see because yeah it's it's not
self-evident if it were every other
person would become a buddha
so the buddha was able to see despite
the pressure of the world despite being
on the verge of death himself to
starvation and everything else that
those things is not where suffering is
truly rooted in
it's the craving like literally internal
craving of your mind
absence of that craving regardless of
circumstances means peace
to the point where he said even if
highway robbers grab you pin you down
chop your limbs one by one if you
fulfill the teaching you won't suffer on
account of it not that you will not
experience the discomfort but internal
pain of the mind cannot be experienced
ever again that's what he called
unshakable liberation
not unshakable control of the world
whereby nothing bad happens to you ever
again quite the opposite
he's just in unable to have the
phenomenon of craving present in your
mind thus unable to suffer
that is the craving for
out there isn't it
for things phenomena
states yes it's kind of craving that's
yes it's kind of craving that's
perpetrated through these actions that
are rooted in desire real will and
that's we go back to the training of the
precepts it's not like
uh a commandments that you must obey it
it's just like that's what that's what
keeps fueling the fire the problem
so that's why you do it until you
approach it then afterwards do what you
like but there'll be certain things
you'll be unable to do act out of
craving and desire yeah
so there's kind of hope in society that
even they are
occupied with their
lay life with family jobs living society
they can still develop this mindfulness
wisdom and
right view
yeah so this kind of hope it's kind of worth
so this kind of hope it's kind of worth
to pursue this path and make an effort
yeah he's just as i said like
work is
comes down to keeping the presets
sense restrained
being able to contain
your desires to the point to see where
this craving is and what you're supposed
to see
so that doesn't mean that you can just
go on and do stuff you used to do when
you didn't want to practice like to some
extent your life will probably have to
start tailoring what you want to achieve
so you can't be unrestrained going with
you know people with you know they would
sort of take you in these wrong
directions it's like again i want to train my dog
it's like again i want to train my dog
but i let it run with the wild pack of
you know
jackals and stuff well it's not going to
become tame it's going to become wilder
so to some extent circumstances need to
sort of be kept in check but yeah you
don't need to go and live on top of a
mountain or somehow because that's just
might result in even more ignorance one
thing we quite often emphasize is
actually also
okay seclusion from
sensuality sound but also seclusion
physical seclusions
uh
yes but again i wouldn't worry about that
but again i wouldn't worry about that
much in the beginning
that is useful later on but
uh it's really the
keeping the presets those are the the
the rules of training let's say like
that the rules of engagement so
if the circumstances you're in
keeps making you break the precepts then
you need to start revising a bit just
from that practical standpoint
if
the circumstance does not push you to
break the precepts then fine keep places
keep practicing read the suitors reflect
and so on and then yes if you have time
spend more time in seclusion without
distractions and so on but that's not
something oh i must aim for that and
that's where my practice will begin
that sometimes people will have that
view as well
a different way of approaching this
might be
by asking you what would you say that
from the perspective of say the more um
older or traditional or suta buddhism
from this perspective
be some of the most common
misconceptions or
fallacies or problematic views that
people usually associate with buddhism
in contemporary ways so which are the
things that you come across that you
think are
well i think the first yeah the first
and obvious one is
i think people think uh meditation leads
to enlightenment as in i don't have to
do anything else i just need to learn
how to meditate and enlightenment will
happen to me
and there are plenty of schools
you know non-buddhist and later
buddhists they would be teaching that
but it's nowhere near
the original instruction
the second common thing would be
buddhism is for the world peace or
something like that
there was never buddhist concern either
it's it's just
those are kind of not necessarily
something that would block people's
progress but it can certainly take them
in the
different directions of learning i
suppose so
it's it's fine people can choose to go
wherever they want but i think the most
important thing is to at least at least
know the difference like knowing that
that what what the kind of original
instruction was
and what what what it was concerned with
let's say that and they're not confusing
it for other other things you come
across
okay uh related to this maybe a sub
question would be um
i would assume that
a lot of people in contemporary society
would have issues with this emphasis on
uh trying to somehow transcend
desire given the fact that desire in one
way or another
is basically
the foundation on which the contemporary
society is pretty much built and a lot
of people um
do
[Music] about do do subscribe to some version of
about do do subscribe to some version of
this hedonistic or semi hedonistic
worldview or if they don't they would at
least want to retain this idea of well i
can still
enjoy my desires without falling prey to them
my desires without falling prey to them
so how would one
bring closer to the contemporary
uh um
person this notion of
why desire is ultimately unfulfilling for
desire is ultimately unfulfilling for
unfulfilling i'm actually here kind of
hinting at that lovely video very short
video that you made
it was one of your first ones i think
where you basically show why desire is
unfulfilling no one wants to
fundamentally no one wants centrality of
that one huh
well again even that video will make
sense only to a person that kind of is
already aware of its own situation if
you just say to anybody randomly they're
not gonna see it so
you you can't bring this
the the original instruction will never be
the original instruction will never be
mainstream in the i mean he was
mainstream when the buddha was alive
that's it
after he passed away it started to
decline because it goes against the
whole world i mean that's what he
himself said the one who practices swims
against the stream
going against the grain
of samsara in the world that has its own
direction so
going around preaching to people that
desires are bad it's just
not not really going to work
but those that are willing that do
recognize that are dissatisfied with you know
that are dissatisfied with you know
their mind or the kind of the certain
aspects of their situation then they
could perhaps hear it
or at least know the difference and then
maybe choose to do something about it
so in other words
person that wants to be helped can be
helped otherwise
okay so what what if still we we do not
like let's say completely abandon this
proposition or this idea and maybe we
have someone let me paraphrase this
maybe we have someone who says i i do
have a sense that something is off with
sensuality and desire but i don't have a
clear picture as to why it is
how would you articulate it in a way
that i can see because people are
constantly saying no no look you know
so basically what you what you're asking
is how can
you show the benefit of being free from
sensuality to a person who is refusing
to give up sensuality
so the only way for them to see the
benefit of it is to give it up
and there was a suit that says it's like
person at the bottom of the mountain
wants to know what is the view like from
the top
i mean i can describe it to you
but only way for you to know is to do
what i'm telling you to do in terms of
follow the instruction and free yourself
from desire and then you'll see it for
yourself any other answer i give you even if it's
any other answer i give you even if it's
the right answer for me will not be
understood by you because you're still
not free from it
it's a lot like talking to addicts isn't
it
well in a way that's yeah what
sensuality is yeah addiction that we
know is just the extension of the same
principle of centrality yeah
you can have faith
in the sangha for example because this
is the people that you see you see you
guys seem pretty happy you're you know
you and you you have yeah but again
that's all again that is all secondary
you know that can be a pleasing sight to
you but fundamentally if you're not making
but fundamentally if you're not making
the internal effort to restrain your
mind calm me down understand it makes no
difference it's just a pleasing sight
nothing else just an agreeable thing
because otherwise it's shifting
responsibility exactly that's the whole
point yeah but you said i'd be happy so
well the buddha said you'll be happy
yeah yeah if you if you if you free
yourself from things that are you know
pressuring you and making you act and
controlling you
complaint like this so i have freed
myself from all craving and yet i'm not
happy so you've never heard anyone say
that no that's impossible because
possible
because if you if you uh remove this
source of suffering
the gateway of suffering there can be no
suffering but is happiness something we
should strive for or is it peace it
depends what you define exactly because
is is peace what's making you happy is
being being calm
not controlled
not perturbed by the changes in your
mind by the changes is that what making
you happy or is satisfying my desires
making me happy
that's why oh just do what makes you
happy it's not a standard that you want
world to follow
because happiness can actually just lead
to more suffering because we crave more
happiness exactly so it takes wisdom to
recognize what beneficial happiness is basically
basically
it it seems very extreme to me that
basically for the sake of dharma it
doesn't matter the whole world can die
just as long as i'm in dharma
that's the extreme example but that's
what you mean i'm in dumb i don't follow
well don't you
you're fully enlightened you're not
going to lie
and blow the consequences
blow the consequences
yeah because they're not not not your
responsibility
we're all interconnected we're all work
no that's no that's that's we disagree
there i think that's not everybody's as
the buddha himself said beings are
owners of their own actions there is no
interconnectedness you make your own choices and you take
you make your own choices and you take
results for them
so any other questions
you went through a list here